Does the CIA listen through our phones
and laptop cameras? Yes. I hate to say
it, they can take over your smart
television and turn the speaker into a
microphone so that they can listen to
what's being said in the room even when
the TV is turned off. Hello, I'm John
Kiriakou. I'm a former CIA
counterterrorism officer and former
senior investigator for the US Senate
Committee on Foreign Relations and I'm
here today to answer questions from the
honesty box. The first one is What did
the CIA actually do? There are several
answers to that question. What the CIA
is supposed to do, what it is legally
tasked with doing is very simply to
recruit spies to steal secrets and then
to analyze those secrets to give the
president and other senior policy makers
the best information with which they can
make policy. Now, in real life, it's not
that simple. The CIA does whatever the
president tells it to do. That could be
to overthrow foreign governments, it
could be to implement covert action
programs to influence the foreign media,
to even kill people. It just depends on
who the president is and what policy he
wants to implement. What skills make a
good agent? You might be surprised by
the answer, actually. The CIA, when it
recruits spies, when it recruits
operations officers, doesn't necessarily
look for the big buff guy who works out,
you know, every day or six days a week.
They look for people who have
sociopathic tendencies. Not sociopaths.
Sociopaths are impossible to control
because they have no conscience. They
blow right through a polygraph exam, but
they won't take orders. People who have
sociopathic tendencies do react to a
polygraph, they do experience regret or
remorse. They will respond to directives
and orders. I'll give you an example.
When I first was recruited by the CIA,
I was asked in a group of new hires what
we would do if we got a cable from CIA
headquarters ordering us to collect
information on the Indonesian economy.
You recruit the Indonesian economic
secretary, you make him your best
friend, you spend money on him, your
wives become friends, you vacation
together,
but you learn that he is just not
recruitable. So, what do you do? Well,
one of my colleagues said, "You double
down, work the case another 6 months,
and hope for the best." A second
colleague said, "Maybe you work it
through your wives. Maybe your wife can
convince his wife to give you the
information." I raised my hand and I
said, "You break into the Indonesian
embassy and you steal it." And the
instructor said, "That's exactly what
you do. That's a sociopathic tendency."
What's the coolest piece of spy tech you
ever got to use? You know, there's kind
of a dirty little secret about spy tech,
and it is that 95% of it is purchased
from amazon.com. Seriously. Because it
is cheaper and it is quicker just to go
online and buy it and then use it
operationally than it is to invent it
from scratch. The coolest piece of spy
tech that I ever used was it was a
leather briefcase. I just went into the
local marketplace in Pakistan and bought
it. I think it cost the equivalent of
like $10.
And over the course of 3 days, one of
our technical officers pulled the
threads out of it, installed a wire all
the way around the briefcase, which
could act as a listening device, and
then packed the area around the wire
with these little teeny tiny batteries
that I had never seen before. And then
he sewed the whole thing closed again.
So, I walked into a meeting with my
little briefcase. The bad guy took the
briefcase from me, opened it up, looked
through it. It didn't have anything in
it cuz it was all sewn into the lining.
And we sat there and had the had the
meeting while my colleagues half a mile
away were able to listen to the entire
thing. It was very cool. Does the CIA
listen through our phones and laptop
cameras? Yes. [music] I hate to say it.
There was a dramatic leak in 2017 that
the CIA came to call the Vault 7
disclosures.
Gigabytes worth of documents leaked by
a CIA technology engineer. What he told
us was that the CIA can intercept
anything from anyone. Number one. Number
two, they can remotely take control of
your car through the car's embedded
computer. To do what? To make you drive
off a bridge, into a tree, to make you
kill yourself, and make it look like an
accident. They can uh take over your
smart television and turn the speaker
into a microphone so that they can
listen to what's being said in the room
even when the TV is turned off. God
[snorts] knows what else that they can
do that uh that hasn't been leaked.
Are hit men real? Yes. At the National
Security Council, there is a committee
that meets every Tuesday morning at 9:00
to draw up something called the kill
list. They sit around a table and they
make a list of all the people that they
want to kill that week. And then they
take it back to the CIA which has a
dedicated unit. I won't tell you the
name, but it has a dedicated unit that
takes receipt of the list. They say,
"Okay, number one." They drive to the
airport, they get on the plane, they go
out to that country, they kill the
person, they come back, and then they go
to number two on the list. That happens
every single week. Now, we can have a
conversation about whether that's right
or or it's wrong. it's certainly
immoral.
It's illegal, but it's been tasked by
the president. At the same time, they
will tell you there hasn't been another
9/11, has there? Maybe it's cuz we're
out there killing people.
>> What kind of people would be on that
list?
>> Oh, the the most dangerous terrorists in
the world, or at least people that the
CIA deems to be the most dangerous
terrorists in the world. How does the
CIA recruit spies in foreign countries?
Ah, that cuts right to the to the very
heart of what the CIA is. The CIA trains
its officers
in something called the asset
acquisition cycle. It has four steps:
spot, assess, develop, recruit. So,
let's say you're a brand new CIA officer
overseas, you get out there and mingle
and go to diplomatic cocktail parties or
go anywhere where there might be a
viable target for you. You spot the
target, you go up, "Hi, how are you? I'm
the new officer at the American Embassy.
I'm covering political affairs or
economic affairs or trade or whatever it
is you're doing. You exchange business
cards. That's spotting. Assessing is I
say, "So, what do you do for a living?"
If you tell me that you do something
that I'm operationally interested in,
that's my assessment of you.
Then I develop you. That's actually the
fun part. That is us going to lunch and
going to dinner, and I spend money on
you because I have literally an
unlimited budget to do so, and maybe we
go on vacation together, and our wives
are friends, and you mention offhandedly
that you like to go fishing, let's say.
So, I charter a boat for [music] $4,000,
and I take you deep sea fishing because
you could never afford to do it on your
own, and then we become best friends.
And because we're best friends, I say to
you, "Hey, would you do me a favor?
Yeah, I'm sorry to ask, but you know,
the Russians have this new tank, and I
know that you guys have access to the
plans, and I would really appreciate it
if you could just make me a copy of
those plans. I know that sounds kind of
funny, but it would help me a lot. So,
hey, thanks. I appreciate it. Give me
the I I'll pick them up tonight. And
then, maybe I start giving you a little
bit of money. And then, finally, when it
comes to the recruitment, I say, "I
haven't been totally honest with you.
I'm actually a CIA officer undercover.
Are you okay with that? You're a great
guy, and you're my best friend. And how
about if I give you $5,000 a month, and
you just answer my questions, right?
That's cool, right?"
>> [music]
>> And you undoubtedly will say yes, and
the rest is history.
>> It'd be a good actor to do that, pull
that off.
>> [laughter]
>> And a sociopath. Do you ever fear for
your life? Not now, but over the course
of my career, I did several times. And
I'll give you one example. There were
two active assassination attempts
against me.
In one, I just got lucky, and
unfortunately, my next-door neighbor was
killed instead. He was the British
defense attaché in Athens, Brigadier
General Steven Saunders. I think about
it every single day. In another, an
enemy country sent one of its officers
and a double agent to kill me, but we
had advance warning that it was going to
happen, and we were able to Well, we
were able to neutralize the threat, as
they say in the movies. But there was
another experience that I had that
troubled me deeply. I was serving in
Pakistan at the time. And I was staying
in a small guest house because it was
safer than a big hotel. Sure enough, the
big hotel was blown up, and 45 people
were killed while I was living there.
But I left my guest house at a different
time, like I did every day, and took a
different route, like I did every day,
to go to work. And I noticed that a man
on a motorcycle wearing a red helmet was
trying very hard to stay in my blind
spot. I worked 12, 14 hours, whatever it
was that day, and I left, and it was
dark. And sure enough, there he was
again. There's a definition of
surveillance, it's multiple sightings at
time and distance. So, I've seen him
multiple times at different times of the
day and at different places. I'm
definitely under surveillance. I got up
at 5:00 in the morning, got in the car,
drove a block, there he was again. So,
when I got to the uh to the office, I
said to the security officer,
"I am under surveillance. I'm 100% sure
that I'm under surveillance." He said,
"Well, let's wait until the uh the chief
comes in." When the chief finally came
in, I told him the story, and he said,
"Well, you know what you have to do."
I said, "I know. I'm going to kill him
if I see him this afternoon." I was
worried about it all day, and all my
co-workers came up to me that day to
slap me on the back and say, "Don't
worry. We're all going to be out there.
We're going to have a whole security
team." I said, "I know, but I never
killed anybody before, and I'm so
worried that he's going to kill me
before I get a clear shot at him." That
afternoon, I had a meeting at a safe
house that we shared with the local
service.
And on my way out at the end of the
meeting, and I don't know why I did
this, but I turned around and I said,
"General, are you following me?" And he
said, "No, why?" And I said, "Because
I'm under surveillance, and if I see
this guy again, I'm going to kill him."
And I never saw him again.